Guide to the Chauncey Pratt Williams Writings on the American West
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Chauncey Pratt Williams Writings on the American West
1916-1953
WA MSS S-2989
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
2.5
(6 boxes)
Writings by Chauncey Pratt Williams and others on the history of the American West. Includes research material, correspondence, manuscripts, typescripts, and published works by Williams, as well as published works by other writers. Williams' writings include works on the trappers Antoine Robidoux and Bill Williams; the United States General and United States Senator from New York Philip Schuyler; and the Western frontiersmen John Hoback and John Coulter. Also included are Western history publications, including Overland Monthly and The Old West Series.
Williams, Chauncey Pratt, 1860-
Arrangement
Organized into two series: I. Writings by Chauncey Pratt Williams, 1916-1934. II. Writings by Others, 1920-1953.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Source unknown.
Biographical / Historical
Chauncey Pratt Williams (1860-circa 1936) wrote on the history of the American West and collected writings by others on the region.
Scope and Contents
Writings by Chauncey Pratt Williams and others on the history of the American West. Includes research material, correspondence, manuscripts, typescripts, and published works by Williams, as well as published works by other writers. Williams' writings include works on the trappers Antoine Robidoux and Bill Williams; the United States General and United States Senator from New York Philip Schuyler; and the Western frontiersmen John Hoback and John Coulter. Also included are Western history publications, including Overland Monthly and The Old West Series.
French Americans -- West (U.S.); Fur traders -- West (U.S.) -- Biography; Pioneers -- West (U.S.) -- Biography; Trappers -- West (U.S.) -- Biography; United States -- Territorial expansion; West (U.S.) -- Discovery and exploration; Colter, John, approximately 1775-1813; Hoback, John, -1813; Robidoux, Antoine, 1794-1860; Schuyler, Philip John, 1733-1804; Williams, Chauncey Pratt, 1860-; Williams, Bill, 1787-1849
- Writings by Chauncey Pratt Williams, Series I
  - Antoine Robidoux
    - Notes, correspondence, and clippings, 1916-1932 (Box 1)
    - Typescripts, 1934, undated (Box 1)
  - Bill Williams: The Lone Elk
    - Correspondence regarding the publication of Old Bill Williams, 1920-1935; 3 (Box 1)
    - Notes and clippings, 1927-1933 (Box 1)
    - Notes and clippings, 1927-1933; 3 (Box 2)
    - Research notes, 2 (Box 2)
    - Typescripts, 1928, 1931, undated; 3 (Box 3)
    - Lone Elk published in The Old West Series, 1935-1935 (Box 3)
  - General Philip Schuyler
    - Typescript, circa 1930 (Box 4)
  - Hoback
    - Notes and correspondence, 1926-1926 (Box 4)
  - John Coulter
    - Notes and correspondence, 1920-1925 (Box 4)
    - Typescripts and carbons, 1930-1930 (Box 4)
    - John Coulter: Discoverer of Yellowstone Park by Stallo Vinton (New York: Edward Eberstadt, 1926), 1926-1926 (Box 4)
- Printed Material, Series II
  - Edward Eberstadt Americana catalogs, 1937-1953 (Box 5)
  - Kit Carson's Own Story of His Life. Taos, New Mexico: Santa Fe New Mexican Publishing Corporation, 1926., 1926-1926 (Box 5)
  - The Old West Series, 1934-1936 (Box 5)
  - One Hundred Years Ago in Old Taos, Touring Topics, 1927, 1930 (Box 5)
  - Overland Monthly, The Mentor, 1920, 1925-1926; 2 (Box 5)
  - Overland Monthly, 1926 June; 2 (Box 6)
  - Missouri Historical Society publications, The Colorado Magazine, Touring Topics, 1923-1930 (Box 6)
  - Quarterly Journal of the New York State Historical Association, 1928 October (Box 6)
  - Scribners, 1927 February (Box 6)